<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle [s]ent to divers [pa]pistes in England prouing [th]e Pope to bee the beast in the [1]3 of the Reuelations, and to be the man exalted in the temple of God, as God, Thess. 2.2 ... / by F.K.</title>
            <author>Kett, Francis, d. 1589.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04809</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14944.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2164</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23095838</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23095838</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26218</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04809)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26218)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1797:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle [s]ent to divers [pa]pistes in England prouing [th]e Pope to bee the beast in the [1]3 of the Reuelations, and to be the man exalted in the temple of God, as God, Thess. 2.2 ... / by F.K.</title>
                  <author>Kett, Francis, d. 1589.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Marsh,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[P]rinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1585.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: A dehortation from papistry.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Francis Kett.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [pi]³ A⁴ C-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26218:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26218:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AN EPISTLE</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ENT TO DIVERS <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>piſtles in England, prouing</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pope to bee the Beaſt in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>3.</hi> of the Reuelations, and to <hi>be the man exalted in the</hi> Temple of God, as <hi>God. Theſſ. 2.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereby the true Church of</hi> God, and the good profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpell, is know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en from the euill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y hereby haue beene conuerted of late. by F.K.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>igence to make thy election ſure.
<bibl>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n eternall life, whereunto thou are called.
<bibl>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>RINTED AT LONDON by Henry Marſh.</p>
            <p>158<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26218:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26218:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE MOST</hi> Reuerend father in God, <hi>Iohn, biſhop of London, long</hi> health and felicity in Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing ſtirred vp, (moſt Reuerende father in God) with the ſweete exhortation of Paul, who ſayth, in ſpirituall thinges I would not haue you ignoraunt, but couet ſpirituall giftes, and moſt chiefely for to propheſie, which doth edefie, exhort and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort: I thought it good, ſeeing the church of God toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ſtormes, through the depe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:26218:3"/>
of Sathan, who roreth like a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring Lion, and worketh the ſpirit of error in mens harts, &amp; ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth tares among the wheat of the Lord, to laboure in the vineyard of ſpirituall vnderſtanding, by the goodnes of the vnſpotted Lambe, who openeth the booke with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſeales, wherein the whole ſtate of his Church is reuealed, in what caſe it ſhall ſtand, from his aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, till his comming in glory. Touching which Reuelations, with all the miſteries of the Scripture, I hauing written a booke at large, called the golden cloſet, and Key that vnlocketh heauenly miſteryes,
<pb facs="tcp:26218:3"/>
and another called the glorious gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of mans glorification, thought it good, in the meane time, hauing ſent this epiſtle and others to diuers Papiſts in England (touching whom a good worke by the grace of God is wrought) to dedicate this ſame vnder your protection, hopyng that as it hath done good to others by writing, ſo by Print it may doe much more, if it ſhall pleaſe you of your good fauoure and Heauenly giftes, wherewith you are knowen to bee fruitfull among men, to the glory of God, and conſolation of Soules, and to the reward of your Heauenly calling in Ieſus Chriſt:
<pb facs="tcp:26218:4"/>
to accept it. Thus I doe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend your Lorſhip in my daily prayers to the keeping of the Almighty.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble to commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Francis Kett.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:26218:4"/>
            <head>An expoſition who is the Beaſt in the 13. of the Reuel. <hi>Ieſus ſpeede vs, leade vs, and feede vs. &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y deſired to the truth of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. When I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered how great a wiſhe <hi>Paul</hi> doth inſinuate towarde hym ſelfe, as to bee Anathemy touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his body, in reſpect to winne his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: I am, or elſe I ought to bee, ſo much thereby ſtirred vp, vpon the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes of loue, as to offer ſome porcion to you and others, of that good gift, and tallent, which the Lord hath gieuen me: If by the grace of God, it may pleaſe you to accept it ſincerely and meekely, that by that meanes the ſpirite of adoption
<pb facs="tcp:26218:5"/>
ſtanding at the doore of your heart, may enter into your inward man, and worke more redely, that ſweete motion in you as not to harden your heart, when tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you heare the voice of Gods holy truth I write not to moleſt your conſcience an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> minde, but to walke with you in the way of perſuaſion, truſting by the powred Gods word (which is ſharper then a tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> edged ſword,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.</note> and parteth the bone from the marrow, &amp; the ſpirit from the ſoule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to perſuade you, by the interceſſion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hym, (beyng a true mediator for euer who ſitteth in heauen, on the right han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Father, before whom we muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peare in Iudgement to make an accomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at the great and feareful day of the Lord that you will be ſo much contented, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the will of God, as to deliberate with be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter aduiſement, touching that ſentence of S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.</note> who ſayth, worke out thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation with feare and trembling. And alſo touching the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> which ſayth: Vſe all diligence to make thy ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb facs="tcp:26218:5"/>
ſure. Wherein we are ſufficiently counſelled, how much it ſtandeth euery man in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to looke to the ſauing health of his ſoule, which is ſo ſweete and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe; conſidering that there is a way to ſaluation, and a way to perdition.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Timoth.</hi> 2.2.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ought deepely to conſider of that ſentence of <hi>Paul,</hi> which ſayth, that if a man ſtriue for a maiſtry, hee is not crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, except hee ſtriue lawefully. For which cauſe I am moued in the tender kindnes, which my ſoule beareth toward all ſoules, to deſire you, in the ſpringling of Chriſt his bloud, that you will looke ſo carefully into your ſelfe, as that you may bee ſure (by grace) ſo to ſtriue and ron, as that you may win the crowne of eternall life.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10.</note> For S. <hi>Paul</hi> willeth vs to bee moſt vigilant, when hee ſayth, you that ſeeme to ſtand take heede you fall not. So that let not preſumption or ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſtop your eares from the truth, and cary you away to vnknown ceremonies, but firſt proceede with ſincerity of hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
<pb facs="tcp:26218:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26218:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26218:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26218:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26218:8"/>
and pure praiers offred vp to god, intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to geeue you his wiſedome, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to S. <hi>Iames.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames.</hi> 1.</note> If any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lacke wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome let him aſke it of God, and he ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it: aſk in fayth &amp; wauer not &amp;c. And with this order, in heart examine your ſelfe, for God knoweth the ſecrete moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all mens heartes, and then pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what I write to you, and I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded in my fayth, that you ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently feele the ſpirite of adoption to moue your ſpirite, and to leade you into all truth; alwayes prouidyng, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining of your owne conſcience, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the fleſh, the world, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, which ſtriue agaynſt man, to holde hym backe in the dungeon of darkenes, by contrary reſiſtance of minde, through the ſpirite of error, which is buſy in all mens thoughtes. Whereupon it ſtandeth you and all vs the more in hand, to looke to the foundation of our Saluation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3.</note> leſt that wee buyld vpon a ſtraunge founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or elſe doe buyld timber and ſtrawe
<pb facs="tcp:26218:8"/>
vpon the foundation which the Apoſtles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue layde, and ſo vndiſcretly ron with <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leu.</hi> 10.</note> bringing ſtraunge fire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore the Lord, and ſo be in daunger of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Lordes conſuming fire. Wherefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et me perſuade with you, to vſe no other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yne, then the golden rodde of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to meaſure your religion with all, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt that you leaning to much to traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, doe decline from the meaſure of the Goſpell, when as God ſayd ſtreightly to <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.</note> (buildyng the tabernacle) ſee that thou doeſt all thinges according to the pattern which was geuen thee. And therfore, Chriſtian wiſedome doth moue vs in the feare of the Lord, to follow the very patern of the Goſpell, if wee minde to walke as children of the day, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the good and true profeſsion. In conſideration whereof, I hope that you will accept this my wryting as a ſweete motion, with examining the deepenes thereof to your conſolation, in a confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med verity of a better profeſsion then as
<pb facs="tcp:26218:9"/>
yet you holde. And now to proceede the grounde of the matter. Whereas o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heauenly Sauiour and high Melch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dech, being aſcended vp to heauen, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vpon his abounda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t loue ſhew vnto Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> how much he did tender his church, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beloued congregation, when as by mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtery of reuelation, he did ſignifie ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and by whome his church and tem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſhould be from time to time, euen to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> worldes end, afflicted and troden down It is then that we conſider how all thing are written for our learning (accordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to Saint <hi>Paule</hi>) and that eyther by hiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry, precept, doctrine, figure, parable<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> myſtery. So that we ought to be caref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> wiſe, and vigilant in vnderſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reuelations.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.</note> For Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayth, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> happy is he that keepeth the wordes this profecie. For which cauſe, I co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> now to the marke, to ſhew by euide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſcripture (by the holy will of God) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is that great Beaſt in the 13. of the Reuel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 13.</note> and who is that ſinfull man that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:26218:9"/>
in the temple of God, as God: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Theſſ. Epiſt. 2. Cap. 2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 2.2.</note> and which Citty is the whoare of <hi>Babilon</hi> with whome the nations of the earth haue committed ſpirituall fornication,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 18.</note> according to the 18. of the Reuelation. To the confirmation whereof that the truth may bee truly extracted, I wyſhe that all mens hearts were opened: Fyrſt by prayer, and then to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of theſe reaſons which enſue. Of the which, firſt and principally, I thus de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare and proue by introduction,<note place="margin">The Turk</note> that the <hi>Turke</hi> is not that Beaſt nor ſinfull ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the <hi>Turke</hi> hath beene an enemy, from his firſt vpriſing, manifeſted to all Chriſtians, whereby it appeareth playnely, that hee is not the ſinfull man exalted in the Temple of God. For S. <hi>Paul.</hi> ſayth that the ſinfull man muſt bee opened at this time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth by the deluſion of <hi>Sathan:</hi> But the <hi>Turke</hi> hath bene alwayes an open aduerſary, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can not bee ſayd to be opened. For
<pb facs="tcp:26218:10"/>
what ſoeuer is manifeſt, can not be ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be opened; but he which is a cloſe, pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uy, ſecret &amp; coulored aduerſary is ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be opened, ſo that the <hi>Turke</hi> is not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſinfull man, and Beaſt named in the 13 of the Reuel. but hee is the very imitate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> who did alwayes ſhew hym ſelfe an open tyrant to the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites.<note place="margin">Preſbiter Iohn.</note> Next to this, <hi>Preſbiter Iohn</hi> of the <hi>South</hi> of <hi>Affrica,</hi> can no way bee ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to bee the Beaſt in the 13. of the Reuela<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, or exalted man in the Temple, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as he doth dwel beyond the middle Sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo he hath little or no conference in reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gion with other kingdomes, but is kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen to meddle little with <hi>Europe</hi> or <hi>Aſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and beſides the ſtate of his Kingdome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch, that neither <hi>Aſia, Europe,</hi> nor <hi>Eaſt India,</hi> do much acquainte them ſelues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the doinges of <hi>Preſbiter Iohn,</hi> who ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> no ſuch ſeate, nor no ſuch Citty with whom the Nations of the Earth ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> committed ſpirituall fornication, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the 18. of the Reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Alſo tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26218:10"/>
Beaſt and ſinfull man, or Whoore of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Great Cham.</note> can not bee applyed to great <hi>Cham</hi> and his Cittyes in the <hi>North Eaſt</hi> of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> for hee was neuer knowne to paſſe beyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his Mountaines, neither any way that the ſucceſſion of the Monarchy of <hi>Babilon</hi> did diſcend into his Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, or <hi>Preſbiter Iohns</hi> Countrey of the <hi>South:</hi> and therefore neither of them can bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way accounted the Beaſt in the <hi>13.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 13.</note> of the Reuelation, and ſinfull man exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Temple of God as God,<note place="margin">Theſſ. 2.2</note> or any of their Cittyes to be the Whoore of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon</hi> in the <hi>18.</hi> of the Reuelation. Next,<note place="margin">Reu. 18.</note> it can not bee the <hi>Emperours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Emperour.</note> for they were alſo open perſecutors of the truth, and therfore being manifeſt aduerſaries, could not be ſaid (according to S. <hi>Paul</hi>) to bee opened.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.2.</note> Neither is it the high King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> or any temporall King of the Earth. For Chriſt to diſcide this whole controuerſy, and to make the truth here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to bee knowne to his congregation, doth manifeſt to <hi>Iohn</hi> by Reuelation, that
<pb facs="tcp:26218:11"/>
hee is a Starre fallen to the Earth, that hath the Keyes of the bottomles pit, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>.9.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 9.</note> of the Reuelation, and that he burneth like a blaſing lampe, and not like a pure candell to bee ſette vpon a Candelſticke,<note place="margin">Reu. 8.</note> according to the <hi>.8.</hi> of the Reuelation. &amp;c. Whereby it being e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, by all the places of the Scriptures, that a Starre doth repreſent a prelate and ſpirituall paſtoure of the Church, as in <hi>Daniel. 12.</hi> and Reuelations. <hi>1.</hi> And this being apparent, that there is no Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late in the World, that doth ſo much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt hym ſelfe as the <hi>Pope</hi> doth; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by true conſequence I affirme the <hi>Pope</hi> to be this Beaſt in the <hi>.13.</hi> of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelations,<note place="margin">Theſſ. 2.2.</note> the ſinfull man in the Theſſa. and his ſeate and Citty the whoore of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon</hi> in the <hi>.18.</hi> of the Reuelations, with whom all nations haue committed ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall fornication.<note place="margin">Theſſ. 2.2.</note> And now that the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Reuelations and the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Paul,</hi> doe agree with the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, proceeding, opening, and darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:26218:11"/>
of the <hi>Popes</hi> auctority, and his ſeat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and alſo that his Citty by ſucceſſion and inheritaunce triumphant is the onely heyre of the firſt <hi>Babilon,</hi> inioying the fourth Monarchy, whereupon, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, proceeding, opening, and dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening, of the ſeat of the <hi>Pope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 16.</note> aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the pouring out of the vialles, and to the meaſuring of the Temple (by <hi>Iohn</hi>) with his golden rodde,<note place="margin">Reu. 11.</note> doe euidently to any ſpirituall minde, ſhew it ſelfe to bee a caſe moſt playne, that the <hi>Pope</hi> is the foreſayd Beaſt: and further to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede effectually to proue this matter, that you may bee rooted in the truth, you ſhall vnderſtand,<note place="margin">Reu. 6.</note> that firſt after the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention of Chriſt into Heauen, that then his Church proceeded pure, his word ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely preached, by his Apoſtles, and ſo proceeded vnder the coloure of a white Horſe,<note place="margin">Reu. 6.</note> according to the opening of the firſt ſeale. After their time it proceeded in the coloure of a red Horſe, repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting bloudy perſecutions, as in the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:26218:12"/>
dayes, as in the ſecond ſeale ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. And after the diuiſion of time it proceeded in the coloure of a blacke Horſe, being contrary to the firſt white Horſe, which was pure religion, for then did ariſe the ceremonies of the <hi>Romiſe</hi> Church, and the exaltation of the <hi>Pope</hi> and his ſeate. Whereupon, his vpriſing being in the fiue hundred yeare after Chriſt, is aunſwering rightly to the thir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeale opening of the blacke Horſe. &amp;c. And to the miſtery of <hi>Iohn</hi> meaſuring the Temple,<note place="margin">Reu. 11.</note> where he is commaunded to ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> out the quire or outward court, which by computation commeth to foure hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred cubites, which repreſent yeares meaning thereby, that whereas the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles</hi> and vnbeleeuing <hi>Emperours</hi> haue perſecuted the Church openly for fow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hundred yeares after Chriſt, that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhould not meaſure that, becauſe it manifeſt, but meaſure the Temple and the Aulter, and them that worſhipp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therein, meaning that ſecrete treading
<pb facs="tcp:26218:12"/>
downe of the Temple and truth of Gods word, that as the meaſure of the Temple and Aulter doth contayne a thouſand two hundred and threeſcore Cubites, (which repreſent yeares) that ſo long ſhall the <hi>Pope</hi> (being the foreſayd Beaſt and ſinfull man, euidently ſhewed and proued) tread downe the verity of Gods truth, which number of yeares doth pricke faſt to his ende. And therefore ſeing that the introduction of the ſeates of Kingdomes, the euent of the cauſe, and the miſtery of the Reuelations, doth ſhew the <hi>Pope</hi> to bee that Beaſt in the <hi>.13.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theſſ. 2.2. Reu. 11.</note> of the Reuelations, and doth ſhew his ſeate to bee of great antiquity, and his conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance to bee till Chriſt come in the Cloudes: it is then an heauy and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched bragge, to boaſt of his antiquity, or to cleaue to his traditions. For the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelations doe ſhewe clearely, that hee,<note place="margin">Reu. 16.</note> and his, began with a noiſome botch, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋiall. </seg>1</label> with bloud, and heate of fire, and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋiall. </seg>2</label> enuy, and hath nowe his feare darkened <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋiall. </seg>3</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋiall. </seg>4</label>
               <pb facs="tcp:26218:13"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋiall. </seg>5</label> by the fift Viall, and ſhall when ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋiall. </seg>6</label> cometh of the ſixt Viall, ſhew with w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſpirite they are ſanctified, in that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vncleane ſpirites like frogges ſhall p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceede out of the mouth of the Beaſt,<note place="margin">Reu. 16.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Dragon, and falſe Prophet, to gather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Kinges of the Earth to battayle agay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> the great day of the lord, which is ſmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> fire, and brimſtone, euen the ſpirite error, enuy, and hypocreſy: and acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋiall. </seg>7</label> to the ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th Viall, their end ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> be with fire, hailſtone, and brimſtone that the brag of their antiquity, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginning,<note place="margin">Reu. 14.</note> proceeding, and ending, is v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lamentable. For the Angell ſayth, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whoſoeuer take the marke of the Bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and will not come away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Babilon,</hi> ſhall bee puniſhed with f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and brimſtone. And therefore I grau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you that hee hath continued a thouſand yeare and odde, and ſhall continue to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> end of the World,<note place="margin">Reu. 11.</note> according as the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtery of the Reuelations doth playne declare: and I graunt you that hee ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:26218:13"/>
the end of the World haue the vpper hand of the witneſſes of the truth: and I graunt you that the <hi>Pope</hi> is wounded (according to the <hi>13.</hi> of the Reuelation) at this age, and that his wound ſhall bee healed agayne, but howe, euen by this laſt looſing of <hi>Sathan,</hi> who ſhall in the end of the World bring forth that two horned Beaſt like a Lambe being that great falſe Prophete, that ſhall doe ſuch Miracles that if it were poſſible the elect ſhould bee deceyued; but alas to theyr great woo. For S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Reu. 13.</note> becauſe they beleued not the truth, but had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in lyes and vnrighteouſneſſe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God hath gieuen them ouer that they might bee dampned, becauſe they receyued not the truth.<note place="margin">Theſſ. 2.2.</note> And that ſinfull man that ſo exalteth hym ſelf in the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God as God, ſhal be deſtroied euen with the very appearau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I am to beſeech you, and all of your profeſſion, to way deepely this that I do write in ſhort, which in an other worke
<pb facs="tcp:26218:14"/>
I haue comprehended at large, for it is the very truth of Gods word and his Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uelations. Wherein if occaſion ſeru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vpon your partes, to haue mee in confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, I doubt not but that you will yel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the ſpirit of God, which will worke it you an effectuall worke of grace, touch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing which, I pray God that ſo it may bee.</p>
            <p>And now touching the ſupremacy conſider that you deceyue not your ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues, for her Maieſty, is an Anoynte Prince,<note place="margin">Cron. 2.</note> and hath the Scepter of <hi>Iuda</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her hand, as well in euery reſpect as kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Dauid, Salomon, Aſa, Ezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ah:</hi> For did not <hi>Salamon</hi> a temperol kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> build the Tempell? Did not <hi>Ioſiah</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the reſt of the good Kinges, correct an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> order that in their Realme that was t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the glory of God, and aboliſh that whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was to the contrary? The very like pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> doth her maieſty take vpon her, as h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> maieſty may lawfully and truely. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therefore take heede of that coloured <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:26218:14"/>
of the <hi>Popes</hi> preſumptuous autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, for it is not of God, but of the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon. Thus praying that your heartes may bee opened vnto all truth, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you to <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> there to ſearch with prayer, that you may make your election ſure, and become to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe a good profeſſion. Fare you well, and Chriſt feede you, leade you, and ſpeede you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am yours to doe you good in the behalfe of the Goſpell, as to my ſelfe. <hi>Francis Kett. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:26218:15"/>
            <head>A coppy of a letter ſent from a gentleman and his brethren lately conuerted.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the light is pleaſaunt vnto hym that hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cleare ſight, but offenſiue to them that are purr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> blinde, ſo it may be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thought betweene profeſſors of religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, which haue the cleare ſight, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which be purre blinde, before the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt light of Gods truth. VVherein a partly with your writing, ſo much mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> by your conference, I haue my ſpiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> reuiued to a greater confidence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward your Religion, then heretofor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I haue had. And therefore theſe are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> requeſt you, that you will ſend mee, my brother, a coppy of your golden clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet that vnlocketh heauenly miſterie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and that I may haue your company <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26218:15"/>
Trinity weeke to bee at my houſe, to conferre both in Diuinity, and alſo in cauſes of ſicknes; for I am much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with the <hi>Hipocondriacal</hi> paſſion. And as you haue done mee good, ſo I will be yours or in no part myne owne, euen till death ſeperate vs from this VVorld, and conioyne vs agayne, with Chriſt in glory.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Dij</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:26218:16"/>
            <head>A coppy of an aunſwere to the foreſaid letter, by the Author.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Reioyſe in that you haue graunted in writing, as otherwiſe by conſent in conference, to be ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in making your ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſure, as not to condemne, nor to contemne the ſpirituall giftes, which God hath geuen me, and the writinges, admonitions, and inſtructions, which I haue ſent you. For whereas you did not conceiue the miſtery of the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, touching the antiquity of the Romiſh Churche and the Beaſt in the <hi>13.</hi> of the Reuelations, ſo you did litle regard the differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the prieſthod of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.</note> which is euerlaſting, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to endles life. The want of the deepe vnderſtanding thereof, did
<pb facs="tcp:26218:16"/>
hold you in error, and doth cauſe mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes to ron ſtill after beggerly cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and Romiſh traditions. And beſides the want of vnderſtanding the miſteries of the Reuelations, and of Daniel, hath with-holden many in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>age of papiſme, whereas the truth her of being liuely deſcribed (as I truſt haue performed it, through the grace of God) will ſtrengthen you in a grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded fayth to renounce the <hi>Pope</hi> and is traditions. Thus intending to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie you with word of mouth, at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he day of your expectation, I will declare to you the deepenes of all the Reuelations, in ſuch ample manner and with ſuch fortitude of reaſons (by Godes grace) as that I hope I ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e yours, and you ſhall bee myne, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſhall be both one in Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:26218:17"/>
            <head>A dehortation.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd now whereas <hi>Dan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> propheſing of th' extre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> abhomination, ſaith, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the time ſhall come th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the great Prince, <hi>Mich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> which ſtandeth on the peoples ſide, ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ariſe vp: for there ſhall come a time trouble, ſuch as neuer was, ſince there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gan to be people, vnto the ſame tyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Which Chriſt doth alſo affirme in 24. of Mathew, ſaying, that then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhall be great tribulation, ſuch as was from the beginning of the World to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> time, that except thoſe dayes ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhortened, there ſhould no fleſhe bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued, but for the choſen ſake thoſe da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhall be ſhortened. Touching the wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt declareth the occaſion and rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of ſuch tempeſtuous dayes of daunge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that there ſhall be ſuch falſe Chriſtes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> falſe prophets, that ſhall doe ſuch m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cles and wonders, that if it were poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the very elect ſhould be deceiued. So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26218:17"/>
it appeareth plainly, that before the end of the world, ſhall great ſtormes of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles vniuerſaly happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, anſwering right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the <hi>6.</hi> of the Reuelation, that when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he two Prophets or witneſſes of God haue ended their teſtimony, which is the preaching of his glad tidinges of his teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes throughout all the world (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the 24. of Mathew, that then the time is come, that the Beaſt in the <hi>13</hi> of the Reuelations, ſhall ariſe to heale his wound by making warre againſt the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers: for by that great meanes of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation ſpoken by <hi>Daniel</hi> and by our Sauiour Chriſt ſhall his wound which he hath receiued by the preachers of the Goſpell) be healed vp agayne, and that through the meanes of that two horned Beaſt like a lambe, whom <hi>Sathan</hi> will and ſhal raiſe vp at this his laſt looſing before the end of the World, to doe ſuch magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all miracles, that if it were poſſible the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lect ſhould be deceiued. For then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it, that <hi>Daniel</hi> ſayth, hee ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:26218:18"/>
be grimmer then all his fellowes &amp;c. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then is the time come, that he ſhall mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> highly exalt hym ſelfe in the Temple <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God as God, according to the Theſſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>2.</hi> whom the Lord ſhall deſtroy wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his owne appearau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, when he comme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the Cloudes, and this aunſwere to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 13. of the Reuelations, that there ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an Image made vnto the Beaſt, by t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> meanes of that two horned Beaſt like lambe, that is the great falſe Prophet that ſhall make fire come downe fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Heauen, in the ſight of the Beaſt and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> people, and then ſhall the dayes bee daungerous and cruell, that whoſoeue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> riche or poore, high or low, that doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> take the marke of the Beaſt, can not b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuffred to liue. By which meanes it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uident, that if the Lord ſhould not ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ten ſuch dayes of tyrany and darken<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> it would goe hard with all fleſh, in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they ſhal be inforced either to hold w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> the Beaſt, or elſe to die for the Goſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> So that then is that performed of <hi>Dan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:26218:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that many ſhall bee purified, clenſed, and tried; but the wicked ſhall not regard it,<note place="margin">Daniel. 12.</note> and then happy are they that ſhall fight the good fight, and ſo put on the ſhield of fayth, as to waite vntill a thouſand thirty and fife dayes, for the Lord will geue them Eagles winges to flie into the wildernes, there to be fed with his holy word, as <hi>Elias</hi> was. And now when this tribulation ſhall begin, ſhall three foule ſpirittes like frogges come out of the mouth of the Beaſt,<note place="margin">Reu. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the Dragon and falſe Prophet, being error, enuy, and hipocre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.<note place="margin">Reu. 16.</note> Whereby that flowing <hi>Euphrates</hi> of the preaching of Chriſtes Goſpell ſhall bee dried vp, by the cruell hurly burly of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 20.</note> being the two laſt heads of <hi>Eſdras</hi> Eagle receiued to the end, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſhall raiſe vp to compaſſe the holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>entes of the Saincts, and then is that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt abhomination of deſolation come to paſſe, ſpoken of by <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd this is it, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth; in the laſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayes ſhall bee perillous times, men that
<pb facs="tcp:26218:19"/>
ſhall reſiſt the truth (as <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres</hi>) withſtoode <hi>Moſes,</hi> and therefore ſhall preuaile no longer:<note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> whereby it is e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uident that <hi>Iacob</hi> ſhalbee turned into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſau,</hi> in that the fathers ſhall then deliue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their ſonnes to death; the brother, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> brother; and the children ariſe againſt fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers and mothers, and put them to death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For then is it that the truth ſhallbe laid in pryſon, equity growne aſide, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes ſtand farre off, conſcience falle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> downe in the myre, pitty ſhutte out, and loue froſen to dead. Whereupon it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth euery man in hand to watch and pray, that hee may holdout to the en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when hee ſhall bee crowned with the crowne of life; for the Angell ſayth, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who ſo euer take the marke of the Bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and commit ſpirituall fornication wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that Whoore of <hi>Babilon,</hi> being <hi>Rome</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſucceſſion of the fourth <hi>Monarchi,</hi> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> be puniſhed with fire and brimſton. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> therefore ſeing it is told vs before, in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>21.</hi> of the Reuelations, that the Beaſt
<pb facs="tcp:26218:19"/>
gainſt the end of the world, ſhall haue his wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d healed,<note place="margin">Reu. 13.</note> and that his ſeate being darkened, ſhall be eſtabliſhed againe, by the two horned Beaſt and falſe prophet,<note place="margin">Antechriſt</note> as in the <hi>13.</hi> of the Reuelations, and that hee ſhall ouercome the true profeſſors of Gods word, and reioyſe ouer them, as in the <hi>16.</hi> of the Reuelations, and that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the great ſecurity after this reioyſing of the victory got ouer the two witneſſes of God, the Lord ſhall come, euen as a thiefe in the night; when they ſhall ſay peace and no daunger, then commeth on them ſodayne deſtruction, as traueling vpon a woman with childe, and they ſhal not eſcape: Therfore we ought to be carefull to worke out our ſaluation with feare and trembling, conſidering what te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtes doe hang ouer vs. And now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what a lamentable expectation this is, to looke for change of Religion, and what a woeful wrechednes it is to beleue in the <hi>Popes</hi> traditions, who is that Beaſt, that ere the end of the World ſhall worke
<pb facs="tcp:26218:20"/>
ſuch tyrany and tribulation againſt the Goſpell, as that the people ſhall bee, by this meanes,<note place="margin">Math. 24.</note> in ſuch perplexity, that they can not tell which way to turne them. Wherfore to comprehend in ſhort that which I minde to diſcourſe vnto you at length by worde of mouth, I exhort you to renounce clearely the <hi>Pope</hi> and all his traditions, and laboure to make your ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſure, by holding the fayth of the Goſpel euen vnto death that your Soules may goe vnto them that are vnder the golden aulter,<note place="margin">Reu. 6.</note> who ſuffred before for the teſtimony of the truth. Hold faſt, for the time is at hand. Yours, in the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Goſpell, euen till Chriſt come in his glory, to cloth vs with our hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly manſion.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>F. K.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Iune <hi>3. 1585.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>The righteous ſhalbee had in euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting remembraunce, hee will not bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayd for any euill tidinges, for his heart ſtandeth faſt and beleeueth in the Lord.</q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 112.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:26218:20"/>
            <head>The coppy of an Epiſtle ſent to Engliſh pilgrems and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts. 1584. By F. K.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am moued by the royall law of God, which is to loue our neighbour as our ſelus, and to doe good to our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; to write to intreate you, (my deſired to the truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Goſpell) to heare and reade the wordes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f exhortation, vnder your duety in the feare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f God, and reuerence to his Goſpell, hoping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat the ſweete motion, and tendernes of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ules health, will moue you hereu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to. Wherin, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rſt I beſeech you to meaſure the breadth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ength, and deapth of your inward man, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he path of your ſaluation, by the ballaunce of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he pure Scriptures, and not by traditions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d decrees, ſeing that the Scriptures are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e to make you wiſe to ſaluation,<note place="margin">Tim. 2.3.</note> through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith in Chriſt Ieſus. Therefore ſeing that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w is the accepted time, yea now be the dayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> health, in which Chriſt,<note place="margin">Reu. 3.</note> according to <hi>Iohn</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th ſet the doore of his Goſpell open, it is high
<pb facs="tcp:26218:21"/>
time that you wake out of ſleepe, and enter with the bridegrome while the doore is op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> leſt you fall into ſtrong deluſion, and ſtum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> at noone day, and looke for light when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> darknes. For which cauſe, ſay clearly am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> your ſelfes, Vp let vs go to our deare count<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>England,</hi> and walke in the light of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Lord, and become true citizens (with all fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full alleigance) to her beloued Maieſty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo vndoubtedly and ſincerely hath linked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſcepter to the ſcepter of <hi>Iuda.</hi> For if thou d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deſire <hi>Ezechias</hi> to raigne ouer <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> diligently walked in the law of the Lord,<note place="margin">2. Cron. 29.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged his Realme of Idolatry, ſet vp againe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> true worſhip of God, and exhorted all his ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iects to follow the lawe of the Lord God: t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> behold bleſſed <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noynted of the Lord, abounding in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> giftes of vertue, gouerning her Realme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cording to the purity of Gods word and tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And if thou deſireſt <hi>Ioſias</hi> that moſt go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> King,<note place="margin">2. Cron. 34.</note> which walked ſo purely in the waye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Lord, that he declined neither on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hand, nor on the right, who when the book <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26218:21"/>
the lawe was deliuered vnto hym, did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y cauſe the booke to bee red before hym, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hym ſelfe red it, and all Idolatyr deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, reſtored the true religion to his Kingdome. Or if thou wouldeſt haue <hi>Ioſophat</hi> that wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the commaundements of the Lord,<note place="margin">2. Cron. 27.</note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oued Gods word ſo intirely, that he ſent his Princes, Leuites, and Prieſtes, to teach in all partes of <hi>Iuda,</hi> which had the bookes of Gods lawe with them, and went about in all the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es of <hi>Iuda,</hi> and taught the people: then conſider in the dexterity of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy gouerneſſe Queene <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> how that her Maieſty is not inferior to any of them, in amplifying the glory of God, and ſpreading abroade of his word. For whereas <hi>Eſdras,</hi> red the lawe of the Lord, plainely, and diſtinctly, to the people, and they gaue ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry earneſt and diligent attendance to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it, ſo our imperiall Princeſſe,<note place="margin">2. Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 8.</note> and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Queene, hath cauſed the word of God to bee plainely red, and preached through all her Realme, by many a faithfull <hi>Eſdras,</hi> that euery man may plainely heare it, and reade it
<pb facs="tcp:26218:22"/>
them ſelfes, to their ſoules conſolation. Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is it then that you ſeeke for beyond the Sea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hath not God promiſed that his Goſpell ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> be preached to all nations, and to euery peop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in their proper Landes?<note place="margin">Math. 24.</note> What then haſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to doe, being an <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> to walke againe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſtreates of <hi>Egypt,</hi> or to wander in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way to <hi>Aſſiria?</hi> Behould ſayth the Lord, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haſt thou now to doe in the ſtreate of <hi>Aegyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to drinke foule water?<note place="margin">Ieremy. 2.</note> or what makeſt thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the way to <hi>Aſſiria,</hi> to drinke water of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> floud? Thy owne wickednes ſhall reproue the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and thy turning away, condemne thee. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſo ye <hi>Engliſh</hi> pilgrems, what make yee in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtreates of <hi>Rome,</hi> or in the way to <hi>Italy?</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> feare that your owne thoughts condemne y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and your turning away, will bring you to he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uy deſtruction, vnleſſe yee repent. O ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore come away, and turne to the treuth, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be not thereof aſhamed, for the Lord kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth your ſecret thoughts, with whom you m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> not diſſemble and halt betweene two opi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, but bee faithfull vnto your Soueraig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Queene, and let King <hi>Dauid</hi> be your exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26218:22"/>
who would by no meanes lay blouddy handes vpon King <hi>Saule</hi> his enemy, being the Lords anoynted. Wherefore yee <hi>Engliſh</hi> Romaines, examine your ſelues, try out the deapth of your conſcience, remember the dreadfull day of Iudgement, and be no longer deceyued, for loe how wreched your ſtate is, to flie the light of the Goſpell, to ſeperate your ſelues from your alleiga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to hope for a day by miſchiefe.<note place="margin">Eſay. 30.</note> Know yee not, that it is a woe, to forſake the counſell of God, to ſeeke and ſticke to the counſell of men? and knowe yee not that the (Lord ſayth) woe bee thoſe ſhrinken children, which take a web in hand, but not after my will. Then ſee what web is this of youres, to truſt in pardons &amp; indulgences, to commit ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to Saintes, to hope to be reskewed out of the paynes of fayned purgatory, by a maſſe, to buylde true godlines vpon outward cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyes and ſolemnities, and to hold the word of God in an vnknowne language;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.</note> knowe yee not that Paule ſayth, that, whatſoeuer is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, is light? how can you then hold in true conſcience that ſuch kind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of religion is the
<pb facs="tcp:26218:23"/>
light, when as they are not manifeſt by the ſcriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es. Wherefore <hi>Paule</hi> exhorteth you not to walke in the vanitye of minde,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4</note> blyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in vnderſtanding: and Chriſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelleth thee to buy of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m pure gold,<note place="margin">Reu. 3.</note> and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynt thine eyes with eye ſalue that thou mayſt ſee. How then can the Latyne Seruice be to thee an eye-ſalue to ſee the truth of Goddes worde, when as thow canſt neyther reade it nor vnderſtand it? Is it not an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certayne ſounde to an ignorant eare which can cary no truth of edifying, when it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded vnto vs, that all thinges ſhould be done to edifye? Then no doubt but that it is Gods holy will that the ſcriptures ſhould be in our mother language, as a pretious eye-ſalu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in our houſe, that we may be eſtabliſhed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Gods holy truth, and not be deceaued. Harke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therfore deare Countrymen, and be carefully aduiſed, and learne to be wiſe to that which is good, and innocent to that is euill, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour not the preceptes &amp; ordinaunces of me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more then the inſtitutions of God; For ſayth <hi>Paule,</hi> he that ſtudieth to pleaſe men, is no
<pb facs="tcp:26218:23"/>
the ſeruaunt of God:<note place="margin">Galath. 1.</note> and the Gospel (ſayth he) which I preach, I receaued it not of men. Therefore take heede how yee looke after the traditions of men and follow ſuperſtitions, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the word of your ſaluation commeth not from men, but from God. And now ye ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naryes &amp; Ieſuites, you enter into mens hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes like ſmokie fire-brands, you take in hand to enforce the people after your wayes, that were eſcaped bondage Doe ye not respect the daunger which is toward them that ſeeke to deuour ſoules, &amp; put ſtumbling blockes, like Balam, before the people? It ſtandeth you vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to examine the ſcripturs what foundation you doe lay, leſt if you recant not, you prooue yourſelues the Locuſtes which come out of the bottomles pitte.<note place="margin">Reu. 9.</note> Doe ye ſtill ioyne the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Aron</hi> &amp; the order of <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> ioyntly as in one religion, when Chriſt hath tranſlated away the prieſthoode of <hi>Aron</hi> with all his ceremonies? then it can not bee that your doctrine &amp; religion can be good, ſeeing ye mayntayne that which Chriſt hath aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. For which cauſe I beſeech you all to
<pb facs="tcp:26218:24"/>
ſearch the difference of theſe two Priſthods, and ſeperate them as they ought to be, and I am aſſured, that Gods grace will enter into you, to ſee preſently how far you decline from the purity of Chriſt his Gospell, that you ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be reformed to your ſoules conſolation. Wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore (deare Countrey-men) dearely bough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with the bloud of Ieſus Christ, I pray to God that ſuch may be the fruites of this our age that the eyes of the blinde may be lightened and the eares of the deafe opened, that in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wildernes Wells may ſpring,<note place="margin">Eſay. 35.</note> and dry ground turne to riuers: for a woe is preſcribed to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that call darkenes light, and light darkenes and to them that are wiſe in their owne ſigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and thinke themſelues to haue vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding For which cauſe it behoueth vs,<note place="margin">Eſay. 5.</note> to try out th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truth by the fire of Gods holy word, leſt tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we facion our ſelues to be ſeruauntes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bond woman,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> and not children of the free w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man. Wherefore I refer your ſecret though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the goodnes of God, hoping that you w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſider deepely of your religion, and take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>xample of the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> retorned a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er
<pb facs="tcp:26218:24"/>
the destruction of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> into <hi>Aegipt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aying thereby what a daungerous thing it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> renounce the truth and cleaue to cuſtoms, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntiquities, and the actes of the forefathers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing not grounded vpon the pure word of God: For they anſwered <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſaying, as for thy words which thow haſt ſpoken vnto vs in the name of the Lord,<note place="margin">Iere. 44.</note> we wil not heare them; but whatſoeuer goeth out of our owne mouth, that wil we doe: we wil offer ſacrifice to the Queene of heauen, as our forefathers did: for then we had plenteouſnes of victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ales, then were we in proſperity, and no harme happened vnto vs: but ſince we left to offer, many ſtormes of troubles and euills haue gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſwered <hi>Ieremie,</hi> ſaying foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as your ſinnes were ſo greate in ſuch ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, the Lord could no longer ſuffer you, and ſo this is the cauſe of your miſery, becauſe you forſake the truth. The like wounde hath the Lord geuen to you and your whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Papiſty, becauſe of your ſuperſtitious offerings to Saints, and pilgrimages, when you ſay that you had all plenteouſnes. But now the
<pb facs="tcp:26218:25"/>
daies are not ſo agreeable in cheapenes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> therefore beware that you being forewa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the truth of the Goſpell, by many a true <hi>remie,</hi> do not harden your ſelues, and ſay, wil doe as our fathers did, we wil pray to S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, and goe on pilgrimage to ſuch a Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> goe offer at ſuch a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe, for then we ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things cheape; lest that you ſo cutting off truth from you, doe periſh with them of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gipt.</hi> And furthermore, whereas you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſent among vs many of your ſmal writing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gloſes, like ſugred pills, which hauing an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ward feeling of ſweetnes, are notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the full taſte thereof as bitter worm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in that you turne the word of the Goſpell lawe to wormwood, by inducing reaſons o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ceremonial lawe of <hi>Aron.</hi> to prooue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuperſtition which is aboliſhed by Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therfore ſearch the ſcriptures more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditions, that you may gyrd your ſelues with verity, and not hurt by your writings and amples the tender ſheepe of Chriſt. But e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deepely into the bottom of your heart, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider that you ought not to bring ſtraunge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26218:25"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the altar, as <hi>Abihu &amp; Nadab</hi> did: no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore ought yee to make other worſhip then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſpell doth commaund you, contrary to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich, your traditions and ſuperſtitions bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>any; from which waſh you and make you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leane,<note place="margin">Eſay. 1.</note> and then your ſinnes though they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> redd as ſkarlet, ſhall be made whiter then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owe. Wherefore meaſure not the pure reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>n and truth of the Goſpell, by looking to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ife and ſin of the people: but try the truth by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he very Word it ſelfe: For wickednes will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rowe vp among the true profeſſors, in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>athan doth there beare greateſt ſpight, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rawe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into ſinne. Therefore thou people of <hi>England,</hi> make thee ready to mete thy God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd let not thy houſes be ful of voluptuouſnes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd thy Citties full of wickednes:<note place="margin">Ezech. 30.</note> For <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hiel</hi> ſayth that God wil powre out his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation vpon ſinne. Therefore, O <hi>England,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uffer not wilfulnes to wax greene, malitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es to growe vp, vngodlines to take deepe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oote, vnmercifulnes to increaſe: For ſayth God by the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 1.</note> For three or foure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ickedneſſes I will not ſpare <hi>Iuda,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,
<pb facs="tcp:26218:26"/>
Damaſcus</hi> and <hi>Tyre, Moab</hi> and <hi>Amm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> For which cauſe, hate the euill, and loue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> good: and then ſhall we ſtill inioy the ble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dayes of king <hi>Aſa,</hi> who ſayde; Becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> haue followed the lawes and truth of God hath geuen vs peace round about: And God preſerue our bleſſed Queene long to raigne ouer vs, and ſend vs peace in Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>God ſaue the Queen</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
